<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answere to certaine scandalous papers, scattered abroad vnder colour of a Catholicke admonition</title>
            <author>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Earl of, 1563-1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18302</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107637</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843334</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843334</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8058</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18302)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8058)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1167:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answere to certaine scandalous papers, scattered abroad vnder colour of a Catholicke admonition</title>
                  <author>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Earl of, 1563-1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The author's name, [Robert Cecil] Earl of Salisbury, appears on B2v.</note>
                  <note>Includes one of the papers addressed to Salisbury, signed "A.B.C. &amp;c.".</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>All gathering except E are found in two or three different settings or impositions in various combinations.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1603-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWERE TO CERTAINE <hi>ſcandalous Papers,</hi> Scattered abroad vnder colour <hi>of a Catholick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Qui facit viuere, docet orare.</q>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London by Robert</hi> Barker, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>ANNO 1606.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWERE TO CERTAINE <hi>ſcandalous Papers, ſcattered.</hi> abroad vnder colour of a Catholicke Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to recall my Thoughts from the earthly theatre, where they ſate and beheld the variable motions of men, with thoſe cares and cogitations which are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per companions of publike miniſters, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereby to bee made partaker of their contentments, which borrow from publike Action, to giue to priuate Contemplation;
<pb facs="tcp:8058:3"/>I perſwaded my ſelf, that I could neuer make choice of a better Subiect for my medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then of the late Treatiſe, Intituled: <hi>His Maiesties Speach in the late Seſsion of Parliament, together with a Diſcourſe of the maner of the diſcouerie of this late intended Treaſon.</hi> Wherein, ſo many true and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Images of Gods great fauour and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, are repreſented: <hi>(Euery line diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring where</hi> Apelles <hi>hand hath beene</hi>) As all that obſerue the naturall deſcription of this Tree of Treaſon, <hi>amp; in Ramo &amp; in Radice,</hi> may truely ſay,<note place="margin">Cap 6. lib 2. Reg.</note> there needes no <hi>Eliſha</hi> in our dayes, to tell the King of Iſrael, what the <hi>Aramites</hi> doe in their priuateſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. In this Princely and religious worke, his Maieſtie (like to thoſe kings of whome <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaketh, that doe more good by Example then by Lawes) hath increaſed our obligation, by leauing vnder his owne hand, ſuch a plaine &amp; perfect Record of his owne true thankefulnes to Almighty God, for his ſo great and miraculous graces; as neither the preſent Time, nor ages to come can euer be ſo ingrate, as not to retaine the
<pb facs="tcp:8058:3"/>ſame in perpetual memorie. A duety requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God of all his creatures, <hi>Non ad prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium, ſed ad honorem.</hi> For as amongſt all the excellent faculties of the minde (next to the vnderſtanding) Remembrance hath the precedencie, for <hi>neceſsitie and vſe:</hi> So in the accompts of all thoſe ſeruices we owe to God, (who deſireth rather, wee ſhould remember what he hath been to vs, then cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to affect what he is in himſelfe,) Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance is the firſt, and the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. In this facultie we excell die beaſts, and imitate the Angels: For they being preſent beholde at once, GODS Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Loue, in the mirrour of his Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and wee vpon earth, (in the Table of his Workes) haue a preſent and full view of that which God is, by that, which hee doeth. So as, although we cannot ſee him in himſelfe, yet we doe particularly ſee him in his means, eſpecially in thoſe great works of deliuerances and defences, which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth for whole Nations and people, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt publike and priuate practiſes. And therefore if wee ſhall grow forgetfull, or
<pb facs="tcp:8058:4"/>thinke it ſufficient for a day or a yeere to pay him our Tributes of humble thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, when the Heathen themſelues doe continually offer vnto their falſe gods, their Cynamom and Frankincenſe, Then ſhall our errour be no leſſe, then that of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, whoſe prayſe and prayers ended al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt aſſoone as they had paſſed the Red Sea.</p>
            <p>But now while I was in this moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſilent Meditation, (ſometimes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed with the infiniteneſſe of GODS Mercie and Iuſtice, who reſtraineth the power of the wicked, as hee did the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per from the handes of <hi>Paul;</hi> ſometimes comforted in calculating my dayes of happineſſe, to liue vnder a King, bleſſed in himſelfe, bleſſed in his Oliue bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, beloued of men for his integritie and wiſedome, and pleaſing to God for his zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous endeauours, to clenſe the Veſſels of his Kingdome from die Dregs and Lees of the Romiſh grape;) Euen then (I ſay) when my heart was not a little cheared, to obſerue ſo much as the leaſt note of my Name, in
<pb facs="tcp:8058:4"/>his Regiſter, for one that had beene of any vſe in this ſo fortunate a Diſcouerie, (much like to the poore day labourer, who taketh contentment many yeeres after, when hee paſſeth by that glorious Architecture, to the building whereof he can remember to haue caried ſome few ſtickes or ſtones:) Euen then, was I moſt bitterly calumniated, with many contumelious Papers and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quils, diſperſed abroad in diuers parts of the Citie, without any Author, and yet ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually coming vpon me, one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (like the meſſengers of <hi>Iob</hi>) as I could neither deuiſe to whom to turne mee to make my anſwer, nor yet imagine by what hard deſtiny I had drawne vpon me their furie, thus to ſingle me out for a Subiect of ſo much bitterneſſe, in the dayes of ſo great ioy and gladneſſe: Yea euen in the time when I was perſwaded, that they which had diuided themſelues for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake from all Communion with vs in our Religious offices, would yet haue tuned their harps, to haue ioyned with vs in chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Songs for this our happy deliuerance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:5"/>
            <p>Reſting long in this debate with my ſelfe, whether I ſhould now begin a warfare of words, that had ſo long put on an habite of ſuffering, eſpecially againſt any of thoſe, with whom Diſputes are endleſſe; becauſe their ende is clamor, without deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſatisfaction; After I had taken ſecret and faithfull counſell, from the loue and duetie, which liueth alwayes in me towards my Soueraigne, and entred into ſerious conſideration, how eaſily die errors of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Miniſters, may reflect vpon the beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing Princes; hauing alſo heard from Forraine parts, how farre my Name was there proſcribed for a man of blood; I thought it fit in regarde of the place I hold, to take ſome occaſion to expreſſe my ſelfe in ſome cleare tearmes; left any of thoſe clouds which are vniuſtly caſt vpon mee, might darken the brightneſſe of his Royall minde, which hath beene alwayes wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the mildeſt deawe of Mercie and Moderation.</p>
            <p>And therefore although I know, that <hi>Stylus prudentiae eſt ſilentium,</hi> and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb facs="tcp:8058:5"/>well the caution preſcribed by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> in the apprehenſion of ſcattered ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, wherein the follyes of men like clouds of tempeſt are imagedm when they lacke occaſion to power foorth ſhowers of malice, on the heads of Perſons in place of gouemment: Yet finding my ſelfe in ſuch an abſolute poſſeſsion ouer my owne ſoule in patience, as it is not in the power of any calumniator to diſturbe the peace of a quiet minde; I throught it meete to breake ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and to the intent my anſwere might be the better conceiued, to ſet downe firſt the Copie of one of their originall writings; Whereof the tenour followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:6"/>
            <head>¶ To the Earle of Salisbury.</head>
            <p>MY Lord, Whereas the late vnapprouable &amp; moſt wicked deſeigne, for the deſtroying of his Maiestie, the Prince, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, with many others of worth and qualitie, (attempted through the vndertaking ſpirits of ſome more fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; turbulent, then zealous &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaſſionate Catholicks) hath made the generall ſtate of our Catholicke cauſe ſo ſcandalous in the eye of ſuch, whoſe corrupted iudgements are not able to fanne away and ſeuer the fault of the profeſſor from the profeſsion it ſelfe; as that who now is found to be that Religion, is perſwaded, at leaſt in minde, to allow (though God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:8058:6"/>as much abhorring as any <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane</hi> whatſoeuer) the ſaid former moſt inhumane, and barbarous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: And whereas ſome of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Councill, but eſpecially your L. as being knowen to bee, (as the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> termeth it) a <hi>primus motor</hi> in ſuch vncharitable procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, are determined (as it is fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) by taking aduantage of ſo fowle a ſcandall, to roote out all memory of <hi>Catholicke</hi> Religion, either by ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den baniſhment, Maſſacre, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, or ſome ſuch vnſupportable vexations, and preſſures; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by decreeing in this next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſome more cruell and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Lawes againſt Catholicks, then already are made: In regard of theſe premiſſes, there are ſome good men,
<pb facs="tcp:8058:7"/>who through their earneſt deſire for continuing the <hi>Catholicke</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and for ſauing of many ſoules, both of this preſent, and of all future poſteritie; are reſolued to preuent ſo great a miſchiefe, though with a full aſſurance aforehand of the loſſe of their deareſt liues. You are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hereby to be admoniſhed, that at this preſent there are fiue, which haue ſeuerally vndertaken your death, and haue vowed the performance thereof, by taking already the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament,</hi> if you continue your dayly plotting of ſo tragicall Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems againſt Recuſants. It is ſo ordered, that no one of theſe fiue knoweth who the other foure be, for the better preuenting the diſcouery of the reſt, if ſo any one by attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:8058:7"/>and not performing, ſhould be apprehended. It is alſo already a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, who ſhall firſt attempt it by ſhotte, and ſo who in order ſhall follow. In accompliſhing of it, there is expected no other then aſſurance of death; Yet it will willingly bee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced for the preuenting of thoſe generall Calamities, which by this your tranſcendent Authoritie, and grace with his Maieſtie, are threatned vnto vs all. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the difficulties herein are more eaſily to bee diſgeſted, ſince two of the intended Attemptors, are in that weake ſtate of body, that they cannot liue aboue three or foure monethes. The other three are ſo diſtreſſed in themſelues and their friends; as that their preſent griefes
<pb facs="tcp:8058:8"/>(for being onely Recuſants) doe much dull all apprehenſion of death. None is to bee blamed (in the true cenſuring of matters) for the vndertaking hereof: For we protest before GOD, wee knowe no other meanes left vs in the world ſince it is manifest that you ſerue but as a watch, to giue fire vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iestie; (to whome the worst that wee wiſh, is, that hee may be as great a Saint in Heauen, as hee is a King on Earth,) for intending all miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs againſt the poore distreſſed <hi>Catholickes.</hi> Thus giuing your Lordſhip this charitable admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the which may perhaps bee neceſſary hereafter, for ſome others your Inferiours (at least in grace and fauour) if ſo they runne on their
<pb facs="tcp:8058:8"/>former inhumane and vnchristian rage againſt vs, I ceaſe, putting you in minde, that where once true and ſpirituall Reſolution is, there, notwithstanding all dangers what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, the weake may take ſufficient reuenge of the great.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your L. well admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing friends, &amp;c.</hi> A. B. C. &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>It may be your Lordſhip will take this but as ſome forged Letter of ſome Puritanes, thereby to
<pb facs="tcp:8058:9"/>incenſe you more against Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants. But wee protest vpon our ſaluation it is not ſo, neither can any thing in humane likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood preuent the effecting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but the change of your courſe towards Recuſants.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:9"/>
            <p>THis being now one of their charges <hi>verbatim,</hi> becauſe it is not my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to wander further, then the paths of their own vncharitable paſsions do lead me; I will only direct my anſwere to the ſeueral parts therof; though the ſame as they lie, druert me from any other good or regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar methode.</p>
            <p>For the firſt part therefore, wherein this writer in the <hi>Name of the Catholikes</hi> prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth againſt the fact as an vnapprouable &amp; moſt wicked deſſeigne; I muſt ſhortly ſay, that whoſoeuer ſhall read the <hi>Panegyricall</hi> oration of <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> made vpon the murder of <hi>Henry</hi> the third the French king, ſhall well perceiue that ſinne to bee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before the act of <hi>Iudith</hi> to <hi>Holofernes,</hi> by which Gods people were deliuered; and may alſo obſerue in diuers other caſes, how generally our aduerſaries are inclined, to make an ill interpreſtation onely of thoſe thinges, which faile in execution (for otherwiſe <hi>foelix ſcelus virtus vocatur</hi>) to which may be added that which is vulgarly knowen, what number of Authors are illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated
<pb facs="tcp:8058:10"/>ſtrated in Rome, which ſtrongly mainteine the doctrine of depoſing kings. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, becauſe I haue euer loued to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure others by my ſelfe, and alwaies wiſhed that by ſome cleare and conſtant courſe, the ſtate of Chriſtendome might be freed from all pernicious inſtruments, which ſeeke not to plant peace, but to worke confuſion; I haue bin a long time ſorie, that thoſe which imploy ſo many ſeditious ſpirits, dayly to inſtruct the vnlearned Catholickes in thoſe myſteries of depoſing Princes, haue not, by ſome publike and definitiue ſentence ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall (in which it is ſuppoſed the Pope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre) made ſome ſuch cleare explication of their aſſumed power ouer Soueraigne Princes, as not onely thoſe which acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his ſuperiority, might be ſecured from feares and iealouſies of continuall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and bloody aſſacinats againſt theirper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but thoſe Kings alſo which doe not approue his Papal iuriſdiction, and yet would faine reſerue a charitable opinion of their ſubiects, might know how farre to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues in their fidelitie, in ciurl obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,
<pb facs="tcp:8058:10"/>howſoeuer they ſee them diuided from them in point of conſcience. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall attribute moſt to the force of Excommunication, ſhall neuer finde it (if I miſtake it not) further powerfull either by the originall inſtitution, or in the ſucceeding practiſe for many yeeres after Chriſt, then onely to depriue men from ſpirituall graces, and to ſhut them as it were out of the dores of heauen, without ſo groſſe an vſurpation, as to remoue them out of the earth, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their being in Nature. Inſomuch as the writ it ſelfe <hi>de excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and other ſuch like courſes, which are variable in ſundry gouernments, haue rather iſſued from the goodnes of ſuch Chriſtian kings, as were deſirous to worke the better obedience to the Rules of the Church, then from any power of Excommunication in his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all cenſures of the Church hauing left life vntouched, <hi>ſiue fuerat Ethnicus ſiue Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanus:</hi> Many of the heathen themſelues ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taught this for a rule, <hi>Bonos imperatores voto expetere oportet, quoſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tolerare.</hi> And therefore I cannot but maruaile the more at
<pb facs="tcp:8058:11"/>ſome dark and cautelous writings publiſhed of late vpon this accident, &amp; auowed vnder the name of one of their Prime men, wherin he hath beſtowed many thundring words, againſt thoſe which ſhall attempt againſt Princes by priuate authoritie, and yet reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thereby a tacite lawfulneſſe thereof, in caſe it be directed by publicke warrant. A matter no leſſe diſcrediting the ſinceritie pretended in this particular, then that moſt ſtrange and groſſe doctrine of <hi>Equiuocation,</hi> which is ſo highly extolled in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though it teare in ſunder all the bondes of humane conuerſation. For who ſo ſhall pleaſe to reade one place of the holy Father Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (of whoſe Bookes by this occaſion I haue turned ouer ſome fewe leaues) ſhall finde, that when the <hi>Priſcillian</hi> Heretickes in all their examinations before the Rulers of that time, did ſeeke to diſſemble their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, by vſing thoſe anſweres of <hi>Equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> wherewith the Papiſts now maiutaine it lawfull to deny all trueth vnder a mentall reſeruation, and wreſting the words of S.
<pb facs="tcp:8058:11"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> who requireth euery man to ſpeake the trueth to his neighbour, inferred, as if they might ſpeake falſely to all others. This reuerend Father ſoundly and cleerely refuted that irreligious Principle, with this ſhort ſentence; <hi>Corde creditur ad Iuſtitiam, ore fit confeſsio ad ſalutem: Otherwiſe</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>Peter, who profeſſed Christ in heart, and denyed him in wordes, would neuer haue redeemed his denyall with ſo many Teares. This were to take away the Crowne of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, and to make all the holy Martyrs fooles; who, making a conſcience to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with Heathen Magiſtrates, ſealed with their blood the inward thoughts of their hearts and confeſsions of their mouthes. Neither ſhould any man profeſſe this opinion, but hee that ſeeketh to ſubuert all Lawes and dueties of Ciuil ſocietie, breaking out into this Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stulation,</hi> O fontes lachrymarum, <hi>Where are ye to be found, O ye fountaines of teares? How ſhall we hide our ſelues from the diſpleaſed face of Trueth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the ſecond part, where you pretend
<pb facs="tcp:8058:12"/>
               <hi>an apprehenſion of ſo many maſſacres and preſſures to come againſt Catholickes, or ſome more horrible Lawe to bee decreed in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then is already allowed,</hi> and therein taxe me <hi>as one that am like to prooue a fierie Inſtrument;</hi> Giue me leaue to tell you, That thoſe are falſe pretences, which ſome lewd Impoſtor hath vſed as falſe glaſſes to multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your feares.</p>
            <p>Theſe poore Calumniations are like to <hi>Adams</hi> figge leaues, vnable to couer your ſhame. For as hee ſought a couering, <hi>non quia nudus ſed quia lapſus;</hi> So is it your fault, not your feare, that maketh you caſt thoſe vniuſt Imputations vpon your Prince and State. <hi>Sed pereuntibus mille figurae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe men that rule your conſciences, haue firſt dazled your eyes with fearefull, but falſe obiects, thereby hoping to engage you more deepely in their pernicious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</p>
            <p>They haue ſought with <hi>Nero</hi> to ſet Rome on fire, and after to lay the blame on Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Thus hath your credulitie bene ouerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:8058:12"/>with vaine ſhadowes, whereas, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wiſedome are of ſlow beliefe.</p>
            <p>If therefore you had meaſured thoſe things by the rules of Time, and had entred into a true compariſon of things paſt, with things preſent; you muſt needs haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duded better of things to come. For if you behold the precedent Reignes of the two late ſiſter Queenes of different Religion, you ſhall finde more blood in fiue or ſixe yeeres of the firſt, then in fiue and fourtie yeeres of the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Examine likewiſe, whether you haue ſeene ſince this Kings time, any the leaſt prints of bloody ſteps. Hath he added new ſeuerities to the Lawes of the former Time, which he found eſtabliſhed? or hath he not in ſome things qualified them? and in other forborne to execute them, euen vpon thoſe perſons which publiſh with ſound of trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet the ſentence of diuorce betwixt his Subiect and his Souereigntie? Let me ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to your owne conſciences (which in euery man holdeth place of Iudge and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) whether vpon the preſent fury of this
<pb facs="tcp:8058:13"/>fiery Treaſon, which inflamed ſo many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the generalitie of the Papiſts (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to die nature of ſuddaine perill, which hardly admits of ruſt diſtinctions) there hath beene any one acte of blood or crueltie committed; though all men know, that die greateſt violences that could haue beene vſed in ſuch caſes, vnder colour of publicke ſafetie, would haue been interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the true effects of care and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Nam crudelitas ſi à vindicta, iuſtitia eſt ſi à periculo, prudentia.</hi> Nay rather behold the excellent temper of his Maieſties mind, who doubting what the humour of ſudden apprehenſion might produce at ſuch a time, no ſooner had performed his owne publicke duety of Praiſe and Thankſgiuing to God, but hee pronounced in open Parliament how farre he was from the condemnation of the generall for particulars. All which being laid together, I doubt not, but thoſe which are not in the deſperate conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinne, will freely acknowledge his Maieſtie to bee a Prince of PEACE and MERCY, that delighteth nor in the noyſe
<pb facs="tcp:8058:13"/>of Chaines &amp; Fetters, but rather with <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> deferreth Execution, and wiſheth <hi>Se potuiſse potiùs mortuos à morte reuocare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now for the imaginary Power, which it pleaſeth you to aſcribe vnto vs of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel, in which number, as a plotter againſt Romiſh Catholiques, you make me to be one of the <hi>Quorum;</hi> I ſhould take it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes for an Honor and happineſſe, for me to receiue not onely iniury, but perſecution it ſelte in ſo Noble a Societie, where perſons of ſo great Honour and Iudgement are A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; who know full well, that Counſailors of Kings doe ſtand for thousands or hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, onely as it pleaſeth them to place them; and that all their greatneſſe groweth meerely from humble endeauours, no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meritorious then as they are valued by a gracious acceptance. Neuertheleſſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I am made by you a diuided Member from the Body, and graced with ſo hard an Epithete as a <hi>Boutefeu,</hi> and that you are content to borrow my Name to ſcandalize the State you liue in; I muſt freely ſay to you without bitterneſſe, That howſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:8058:14"/>it may ſerue your turne for a while, to make me the marke of your malice; yet thoſe that rightly iudge of the ſpirit in which this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpeaketh, will hardly imagine, that this Faction followeth any other Body, then the Body of Authoritie. It is not the Head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, nor any other particular members that theſe men ſhoot at, but at the Church and Common-wealth; which like <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> Twinnes haue long both wept and laughed together. Theſe are the things which the Enemies of this tithe doe ſtudie to ſubuert, and not any poore greatneſſe of mine, who am onely great in the eyes of Enuy. Nay rather they are angry with <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle,</hi> who bids wiſe Princes keepe downe Faction, which is euer humble till it get the Key of Power. They are grieued, or rather heart-broken, to behold ſuch an Vnitie of State and Councell, as dares bid the world doe, as ſhe would be done vnto. Theſe are knowen ſo well to bee the true cauſes of their Deſpaire and Diſcontentment, as they ſhall ground a faith vpon very weake Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, if they imagine, that open vowes of
<pb facs="tcp:8058:14"/>my deſtruction (a matter of ſo ſmall conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) can make them free from imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of contriuing higher Practiſes.</p>
            <p>But now for that which commeth in the third place, which is their proteſtation, that <hi>for the auoiding new miſchiefe to come, it is intended by good men vpon a ſpirituall Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, to take my life; and that there are fiue perſons vpon the ſecret, but all bound vp by the Sacrament, whereof two are ſo weake and ſo ſickely, as they can hardly forfeit two or three moneths of life:</hi> To theſe I can onely ſay, that hauing their feete ſo nigh the graue, their ghoſtly father deſerues ſmall thankes, that will ſend them thither in bloody cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fins. For they doe neither carrie the markes of Rome Heathen, nor of Rome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: for vnder Heathen Emperours, the victories were ſcorned, which were barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly gotten, <hi>mixtis veneno fontibus:</hi> And when Rome was pure and primitiue, you ſhall finde the Armes of the Church were Teares and Prayers. But now their Oracles are ſo farre degenerate from the former pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of that ancient Church, as they make
<pb facs="tcp:8058:15"/>murder <hi>ſpirituall Reſolution,</hi> and openly threaten the liues of Kings that are Gods breathing Images; when die Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> trembled to violate the skirt of King <hi>Sauls</hi> garment.</p>
            <p>All which conſidered, I doubt not but thoſe Recuſants which doe diſcouer ſuch pernicious ſpirits, will out of the light of this fire perfectly diſcerne the darkeneſſe and danger of that Religion, whereof the faith is lapped vp in ſuch an ignorant &amp; implicite obedience; and ſo much the rather, becauſe it hath fallen out ſo often, that the ſcruples of Conſcience and ſeeds of Treaſon, haue growen vp as cloſe together, as the huske and Come in one eare. And therefore I ſhould thinke that thoſe men, which carie the vnlearned Papiſts, like Hawkes hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, into thoſe dangerous poſitions, may inſtly challenge any that ſhall ſeeke to rob them of the deſerued Titles of <hi>Boutefeux</hi> and fiery matches. For theſe are they that haue made their Church a Court, their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion a vaſſal to ambition, and are ſo hot vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earthly Honours, as they cannot diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb facs="tcp:8058:15"/>
               <hi>Inter ſumma &amp; praecipitia.</hi> Theſe are they that enioyne men to eate their God, vpon the bargaine of blood; where thoſe whom they depraue doe know, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer God doth affect in goodnes, he doth effect by good meanes. And howſoeuer they terme our Sacraments as bare and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſignes; we may iuſtly ſay that wee haue neuer hitherto brought them into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination of murder, or into the houſe of crying ſinnes. As for that ſort of them which pretend to bee ſo full of preſent griefe, through the diſtreſſe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their friends (for being onely Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants) as it dulleth alt apprehenſion of death: Thoſe that lacke charitie, will iudge this dulneſſe to be, <hi>Plus triſtitiae quàm poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae,</hi> more for ſorrow that the proiect hath failed, then that it was concerned. As for the Plotters and ſtratagems whereof they complaine, If thoſe which vſe lawfull meanes to preuent conſpiracies, muſt bee eſteemed Plotters, and Subiects fit for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription; howe ſhall his Maieſtie eſcape their cenſure, that was Gods choſen mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb facs="tcp:8058:16"/>vpon Earth for this particular Diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? Or to what ende doe Princes admit of Councellors care, or Secretaries vigilancie, (whoſe Offices are to ſtand Sentinell ouer the life of Kings, and ſafetie of States) if their endeuours to countermine the ſecret mynes of Treaſon, be thus expoſed to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruction? Or if by ſtratagems thoſe Lawes are meant, by which all branches of Treaſon are puniſhed; why doe they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that thoſe ordinances are deriued from the wiſedome of Parliaments, two hundred yeeres before my cradle? Beſides, if any thinke it in the power of fewe, much leſſe of anyone, to be able to extort determinations of extremitie, or procure new Lawes in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament by ſelfe humour; thoſe neither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the courſe of Law-making, nor the wiſedome, grauitie, or nature of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers in this State, where Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, from whom (as from the Center) all the liues and executions of Lawes take their beginning, are pleaſed freely to admit their Subiects negatiues, with good and gracious acceptation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8058:16"/>
            <p>And now for my ſelfe, with whom you would condition to leaue Plotting, as you tearme it, againſt Recuſants: Firſt, diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on telleth me, that as the Husbandman, which caſteth his eye ouer-curiouſly vpon winds and clouds, doeth neither ſow nor reape in ſeaſon; ſo, that ſeruant, whoſe faith and zeale in the ſeruice of Kings, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth awfull of enemies either for their power or enuy, is neither worthy of fauour nor protection. For when I conſider die Prince I ſerue, that hee hath not taken vp wiſedome of Gouernment vpon credit, but carrieth ſtill the <hi>Iethro</hi> of order in his owne boſome, diſpoſing the meane cauſes, to thoſe that are fit to rule ouer hundreds, and ouer fifties, reſeruing ſtill the greateſt to the greatneſſe of him ſelfe, like a King rich in the experience of many yeeres Raigne, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a free and valiant people, both by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſeat, and education: I freely profeſſe both before mine owne and all other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that although I participate not with the follies of that Flie, who thought her ſelfe to raiſe the duſt, becauſe ſhee ſate on the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot
<pb facs="tcp:8058:17"/>wheele: Yet am I ſo farre from diſauow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my honeſt ambition of my Maſters fauour, as I am deſirous that the world ſhould hold me, not ſo much his creature, by the vndeſerued Honours I hold from his Grace and Power, as by my deſire to bee the ſhadowe of his minde, and to frame my iudgements, knowledge and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections according to his: towards whoſe Royall Perſon I ſhall glory more to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes found an honeſt and humble Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, then I ſhould to command abſolutely in any other calling. For the reſt which may concerne mee in my Religion (howſoeuer darkned with this middle vaile of ſinne and frailtie) it is built vpon the ſacred grounds of Hope and Faith, in the precious blood of my Redeemer, without preſuming vpon any particular merits. And whereas they alledge, that men reſolued to die, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ouer other mens liues; My anſwere is, they haue no more power then the leaſt Spider, who by permiſsion can doe as much. And if the dayes of my life were in their hands; as they might peraduenture take
<pb facs="tcp:8058:17"/>from me ſome moneths of ioyes: So am I aſſured they ſhould take mee from yeeres of ſorrowes. But theſe poore threats a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze no hopes of mine, I am none of thoſe that beleeue with the men of the olde world, that the Mountaines ſhake, when the Moules doe caſt. And farre I hope, it ſhall be from mee, who know ſo well in whoſe Holy BOOKE my dayes are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, once to entertaine a thought to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe a ſpanne of time, at ſo deare a rate, as for the feare of any mortall power, in my poore Talent, <hi>Aut Deo, aut Patriae, aut Patri patriae deeſſe.</hi> For who doubteth that the Magiſtrates who conuerſe with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of ſpirits, muſt not ſometimes vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Tempeſts? All our actions are vpon the open ſtage, &amp; can be no more hidden then the Sunne. If we deſerue ill, we ſhall heare ill; Or if the preſent time doe flatter vs, yet when our glaſſes are runne, (which cannot be long) that glory which maketh worthy men line for euer, dyeth with vs; and our poſteritie ſhalbe the heires of our diſhonor. And therefore <hi>ſuadeat loquentis vita non ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8058:18"/>Beſides, that errour which in all mortall things hath her power, ſtrength and decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; hath now her foundations diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and her Towers taken, ſo as it is to bee ſuſpected, ſhee will play ſo long with the temporall Soueraigntie of Kings, as it ſhall bee the glorious worke of Kings to breake downe her walles and ſtrongeſt defences: And therefore ill becomming ſeruants to ſlacke their pace, for feare of malice, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to reſt aſſured, that vnto ſuch as faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully beſtow their time in the ſeruice of God, the euening and the night ſhall come vpon them naturally one after another: Their faith ſhall aſcend before them, and their good fame ſhall remaine after them.</p>
            <p>To conclude, ſeeing God hath pleaſed to deliuer vs from ſo many vnſpeakeable miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and afflictions ready to haue fallen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, like the viſitation of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> wherof the Prophet ſpeaketh; When their candle hath his cleared light, and when they ſleepe in the armes of peace, loe then ſhall he the time of their viſitation: And ſeeing this ſhould haue happened vnto vs in the dayes
<pb facs="tcp:8058:18"/>of a iuſt &amp; gracious King, when euery man reioyced vnder his Vine and vnder his figge Tree: Let vs both for the honour of our Nation, &amp; the good of our ſoules, be mind-full to informe our ſelues ſo perfectly of all our dueties both diuine and humane, as wee may not become (through our owne groſſe ignorance) the authors of our own confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Let no man ſet ſo high a price on that falſe reputation of keeping oathes to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate friends, as for their ſake to forfeit faith and loyaltie to Prince and Countrey. Will you finde true friends, ſaith <hi>Seneca?</hi> Search them <hi>inter recta officia,</hi> and there ſhall you finde them So ſaith the Canon Law, <hi>Noneſt appellanda fides, quae ad peccatum inuitat.</hi> Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his bookes of Offices diſputing the caſe <hi>inter Patrem &amp; Patriam,</hi> If thy father (ſaith he) intend a Treaſon to his Countrey and State, and tell thee of it; thou muſt firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, after threaten, and after accuſe. For this is a Rule approued; <hi>In promiſſorio prore iniusta, iurans illicitum, obligator ad contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</hi> And therefore ſeeing God hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs ſo miraculouſly from this confuſion;
<pb facs="tcp:8058:19"/>whereof the minde of man (which within a moment ſearcheth from Eaſt to the Weſt) can no way finde the bottome; Let vs make it appeare vnto the world, by the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of our conſtant meaſure of thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, that we eſteeme not this an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary acte of Gods prouidence, nor a thing to be imputed to any fault or fayling in their plots or proiects, but a miraculous effect of the tranſcendent power, farre beyond the courſe and compaſſe of all his ordinary proceedings. Who although hee ſeeme for a time to giue way, as though hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not how men come to their ends and purpoſes; (letting them grow like poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonfull herbes,) yet at length when they are ripeſt, hee will cut them off, and when they are fulleſt of their venimous qualitie, pull them vp for other mens medicine; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made the Scorpion to carry the oyle about him, which cureth the wounds he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. To which let vs adde this further Faith, that as the place where this prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maſſacre ſhould haue bene commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, is the ſame place where the ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb facs="tcp:8058:19"/>of the Primitiue Church, ſhooke off the bonds and fetters of the Romane cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption vnder which it had long continued in ſeruitude: So whiles the ſame Faith ſhall bee Religiouſly and conſtantly profeſſed, that it ſhall neuer be in the power of mortall man, to ſhake the leaſt corner ſtone of that bleſſed and ſure foundation.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I giuen my pen her libertie to runne her ſtage; thereby to free my minde trauelling (as a woman with childe,) with more waighty cogitations then I could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in ſilence, or expreſſe in order; hoping my intentions ſhal receiue a fauourable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſeeing they are bounded with honeſt and humble limittes. If it be ſaide that I haue taken too ſlight an occaſion to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere a ſlander that lacks an Authour; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be thus rightly concerned, that no man would haue ſooner contemned thoſe Shewells or dead papers, which moue with the winde, then I ſhould, if ſo many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements from abroad, and Confeſsions at home (concurring with this calumnie)
<pb facs="tcp:8058:20"/>did not in Iuſtice challendge at my handes ſome ſpeedy courſe to preſerue my poore reputation from theſe cruell aſperſions. In which conſideration, although my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to weare out many dayes, are drawen within as ſmall a circle as my feares, and both my ſpirit and Iudgement, farre from ſuch a deiection or weakeneſſe, as to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, or expect a remooue of fixed reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, by force of Arguments or proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; Yet when I remember with <hi>Seneca,</hi> that euen the great and faireſt Kingdomes, whoſe Lawes abound in bloody lines, doe looſe ſo much of their beautie, as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come no leſſe deformed, then the baſeſt Shambles; and when I know that our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter IVDGE, and SAVIOVR of the World, who alloweth voyces to all kindes of ſinnes, hath made the voyce of blood to ſpeake ſo lowd, as it pearceth HEAVEN it ſelfe: I doe preſume ſo well of all indifferent and equall Iudgements, as my deſence in this degree, ſhall neuer bee held for a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe curioſitie; <hi>Quia Inauditi, tanquam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentes
<pb facs="tcp:8058:20"/>pereunt;</hi> Eſpecially ſeeing mine owne conſcience telleth me ſo plainely, that as Clemencie is the trueſt keeper of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, So Cruelties are of al other the falſeſt Guards. If it be ſaid, I haue bene too ſharpe in cenſuring the Romiſh Catholiques in generall, becauſe I haue beene iniured by ſome Infeſted ſpirits of that Profeſsion; I doe profeſſe ingenuouſly, that I am not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that ſuch a Malice as this, which hath no Paralell, can euer fall into thoſe hearts that hold any ſeeds of Conſcience, or that theſe fiue pretended good-men, which are combined in this reſolution, haue any ſenſe of any Religion at all, but rather that they are ſome diſperſed remnant of that impious Conſort, whoſe eyes and hearts are dayly wounded, to behold ſo many faire Mornings, to follow after ſo blacke a Day, as had prepared miſerie euen for the childe vnborne.</p>
            <p>And when I doe remember vpon the death of the late Queene of happy memory, with what obedience and applauſe, both profeſsions did concurre to his Maieſties
<pb facs="tcp:8058:21"/>ſucceſsion and now obſerue how little aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance was giuen to theſe late ſauadge Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who had gathered together ſome few rotten branches, fallen from ſuch decayed and withered Trees as CHRIST had cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Goſpel, hoping therewith to haue ſet a Fire, and made a combuſtion in the State: Although my prayers ſhall neuer ceaſe, that wee may ſee the happy dayes, when onely one Vniformitie of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is willingly imbraced in this Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie; Yet I ſhall euer (according to the Law of God) make ſo great difference in my Conſcience betweene ſeeing ſinnes, and ſinnes of Ignorance, as I ſhall thinke it Iuſt by the Lawes of men, <hi>Solum necis artifices arte perire ſua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now for anſwere to your Poſtſcript, wherein you ſeeke ſo much to diuert me from ſuſpecting thoſe whome you call Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes to be Authors of this Slander; I haue onely this to ſay, That you ſhould neuer haue needed to put your ſelfe to ſo much paines for that perſwaſion, ſeeing neither the regular Proteſtant, nor thoſe that are
<pb facs="tcp:8058:21"/>vnconformable to the preſent Diſcipline of the Church, can euer be iuſtly charged to haue mixed their priuate differences with any Thoughts, much leſſe with any Actes of bloody Maſſacres. <hi>Et hic baculum fixi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further replyes expect not therefore at my hands: I will henceforth reſt in peace in the Houſe of mine owne Conſcience, where if I doe good deedes, no matter who ſees them; if bad, (knowing them my ſelfe) no matter from whom I hide them: for they are of record before a Iudge, from whoſe preſence I cannot flee. If all the world ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud me, and hee accuſe me, their praiſe is vaine. <hi>Falli poteſt fama, conſcientia nunquam.</hi> If this may not ſuffice, but that you will ſtill threaten and exclaime, I muſt heare with patience, and ſay with <hi>Tacitus,</hi> You haue learned to curſe, and I to contemne:
<q>Tu linguae, ego aurium ſum Dominus.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
